<spelldata>
			<category name="" baseicon="0" decalicon="0">
				<id-00001>
					<casting type="string">Target's Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell creates a protective cushion of air. The magician exhales slowly and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, air rushes in under the target's clothing, pushing outward to create a cushion and providing padding as well as ventilation. The target adds +3 Physical Armor and the effects of fatigue are reduced (GM's discretion). If the target is not wearing clothing or armor he receives no benefit - there is nothing to constrain the air cushion, so it disperses. This spell is popular with elemental fire mining crews working near Death's Sea.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (minutes), Increase Effect (+1 Physical Armor), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 Rounds</duration>
					<effectStep type="string">+3 Physical Armor</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Air Armor</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00001>
				<id-00002>
					<casting type="string">Target;'s Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell enhances climbing ability. The magician crouches down on all fours and then touches the target as he begins to climb and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the target gains a +3 Climbing test bonus.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 bonus), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 Minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+3 Climbing Test Bonus</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Crunch Climb</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00002>
				<id-00003>
					<casting type="string">Target's Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell transforms earth into crystalline darts that fly toward a foe, temporarily rending their armor in the process. The magician flings a handful of dirt into the air and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, his Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted before Physical Armor is reduced. The damage is only dealt once; the duration refers to the armor reducing effect. The target's armor returns to normal at the end of the duration.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Effect (-2 Physical Armor), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">2 Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">WIL +3/Physical and -2 Physical Armor</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Earth Darts</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00003>
				<id-00004>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">2</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell creates an air bed to promote healing. The magician anchors the corners of a blanket with something from any one of the four non-air elements - tree branches, rocks or dirt clods, and the like - then blows into his clenched fist as if inflating a balloon and makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, a cushion of air forms under the blanket, turning it into a comfortable one-foot-thick mattress. Those who sleep on the mattress for six hours gain a +2 bonus to the first Recovery test they make within an hour of waking and are considered to have had sufficient sleep. The mattress remains inflated for the spell's duration or until the blanket is moved or damaged.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Additional Target (+1)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 bonus), Increase Effect (-1 hour sleep required, minimum 4 hours), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">10 Hours</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+2 Recovery Test Bonus</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Air Mattress</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">11</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">6</weaving>
				</id-00004>
				<id-00005>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">2</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell creates a pair of invisible hands which can lift and manipulate objects. To observers, a faint breeze seems to move the target item. The magician wiggles his fingers and makes a Spellcasting (6) test.</p>
						<p>If successful, the Dexterity Step is equal to the Effect Step and the hands can lift up to 10 pounds. The hands can reach anywhere visible to the magician within the spell's range. While they have a tangible effect when carrying or moving objects, they cannot be used to attack, nor can they be attacked.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Effect (+10 pounds), Increase Range (+10 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 Minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Fingers of Wind</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">10 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">11</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">6</weaving>
				</id-00005>
				<id-00006>
					<casting type="string">Target's Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Fire. </i>This spell enflames a weapon. The magician snaps his fingers and makes a Spellcasting test against the wielder's Mystic Defense. If successful, a flame leaps from his fingers and engulfs the weapon in fire, except for the part where it is held. The wielder adds a D6 Bonus Die to the fiery weapon's Damage test. The spell can be cast on weapons made from any material - wood, metal, bone, and so on. The flame inflicts no physical damage to the weapon.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+Step 4 fire damage</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Flameweapon</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00006>
				<id-00007>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Fire. </i>This spell heats food and infuses it with beneficial magic.</p>
						<p>The magician breathes on his hands as if to warm them, causing them to glow a gentle red, then touches a meal and makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, the glow transfers to the food which, within a minute, becomes steaming hot. Eating the food increases the effectiveness of Recovery tests. Consumption of a heated meal adds a +4 bonus to his next Recovery test.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+1 meal)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 bonus), Increase Effect (+1 meal)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 Minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Heats and rejuvenates one meal</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Heat Food</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00007>
				<id-00008>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">2-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">6+ (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>Earth. </b>This spell removes any impurities or foreign materials preventing soil from supporting plant life. The magician points at the center of the spell's area of effect and then makes a Spellcasting test against the earth's Mystic Defense. Soil that is largely untainted has a Mystic Defense of 6; disease-ridden or poisoned earth resists with the Mystic Defense of the disease or poison; earth that is Horror-tainted has a Mystic Defense equal to that of the Horror. If successful, an area of soil is cleansed of impurities and is again able to sustain plant life.</p>
						<p>This spell can be placed in the same spell matrix as Purify Water.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Area (+2 yards).</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Area (+2 yards).</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 Round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Purifies earth and soil</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Purify Earth</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">10 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00008>
				<id-00009>
					<casting type="string">6+ (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Water. </i>This spell removes impurities from water. The magician smears a drop of water on his lips and then makes a Spellcasting test against the water's Mystic Defense. Water that is simply muddy has a Mystic Defense of 6; disease-ridden or poisoned water resists with the Mystic Defense of the disease or poison; water that is Horror-tainted has a Mystic Defense equal to that of the Horror. Beverages with high water content, such as wine, juice, beer, or milk, can be purified by the spell, with all of the flavorful "impurities" removed, leaving behind pure water. The magician's Effect test determines how many quarts of water or beverage are purified.</p>
						<p>This spell can be held in the same spell matrix as Purify Earth.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 Round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower +8</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Purify Water</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00009>
				<id-00010>
					<casting type="string">Target's Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Element [Air, Earth, Fire, Water and Wood]. </i>This spell is five different spells that must each be learned individually. Each allows a character to better handle sudden and prolonged exposure to the specified element. The magician conjures the element upon the palm of his hand and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the element melts away as he touches the target. The target adds +3 to his Physical and Mystic Armor against element-based damage.</p>
						<p>The different elemental versions of this spell can be held in the same spell matrix.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+1 bonus), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+3 Physical and Mystic Armor vs. element</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Resist Element</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00010>
				<id-00011>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Wood. </i>This spell bends and weaves trees to form a suitable place to sleep for the night. The magician stands near the desired location of his shelter, visualizes the form it will take, pantomiming shaping the local flora into the necessary shapes with his hands, and then makes a Spellcasting (6) test.</p>
						<p>If successful, the magician creates the desired shelter suitable for one person per success. The default shelter is rather crude, but effective. Extra threads may be woven to make the shelter more inaccessible, such as hidden at the base of a tree, or in the boughs of trees, increasing the difficulty of any Detection tests by +2 per thread.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+1 Person)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+1 Person), Increase Effect (+2 Detection), Increase Range (+10 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">10 hours</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Creates a suitable shelter for one person</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Shelter</name>
					<threads type="number">4</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00011>
				<id-00012>
					<casting type="string">Target's Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>Area of Effect: </b>2-yard radius</p>
						<p>
							<i>Fire. </i>This spell extinguishes a fire. The magician exhales sharply through his nose, then waves his hand over the fire and makes a Spellcasting test against the fire's Mystic Defense (typically 6, if created by a spell, use the Dispel Difficulty). If successful, the magician makes an Effect test against the fire's Damage Step. If successful, the Damage Step is reduced by -2 per Success. If not completely extinguished, the fire's Damage Step increases by +1 per minute to its original intensity.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 Round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 5</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Snuff</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00012>
				<id-00013>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Water. </i>This spell seals an inanimate object against water. The magician touches a finger to oil, runs it along an edge on the target and makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, the target (which must be an inanimate object) cannot get wet. If cast on an article of clothing, this means water will bead off of it, while if the spell is cast on a container, it will be sealed until it is next opened when the spell will immediately end.</p>
						<p>The target may not be larger than 1 cubic yard.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+1 cubic yard), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Repels water</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Waterproof</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00013>
				<id-00014>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">60-square-yard area, no greater than 20 yards in any dimension</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">2</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>
								<i>Water-Cold. </i>
							</b>
							<b>This spell creates a slippery, icy surface that is treacherous to cross. The magician blows on the surface he wishes to affect and makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, the target area is immediately covered with ice. The spot the magician blows on is one edge of the area - the ice extends from this point, to a maximum size equal to the area of effect. The magician's Effect test determines the Difficulty Number for crossing the ice without slipping. Characters negotiating the slippery surface must make a Dexterity or suitable Talent or Skill test (creatures make a Dexterity or Knockdown test). If successful, they can move across the icy surface at half their Movement Rate. If failed, they are Knocked Down.</b>
						</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Level: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Area (+10 square yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Icy Surface</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">11</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">6</weaving>
				</id-00014>
				<id-00015>
					<casting type="string">Target's Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">2</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Wood. Binding. </i>This spell summons a wood elemental and temporarily binds it to a willing target. The magician places one hand on a tree, then his other hand on the target's forehead and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the target's veins and eyes turn green, and he can hear and understand the slow chatter of wood elementals and spirits within natural areas.</p>
						<p>At any time for the duration of the spell, the bound character may declare they are seeking a living creature. Upon this declaration, the wood spirits will actively begin aiding the bound character in their search, granting a +5 bonus to any tests which may apply. Additionally, the character's Movement Rate increases by 4.</p>
						<p>Once a bound character is on a hunt, any distraction from that hunt causes this spell to immediately end. If the spell ends prematurely for any reason, the target's senses are crippled, suffering a -3 to all Action tests, until he receives a full night's rest, and this spell may not be cast again for a full day. This spell may only have one active casting at a time.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 to search-related tests), Increase Effect (+2 Movement Rate)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Listen and travel swiftly through the forest to find something</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Mantle of the Woodland Hunter</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">11</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">6</weaving>
				</id-00015>
				<id-00016>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">2</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Wood. </i>This spell improves the resiliency of shields. The magician joins his fingers together, then touches the target shield and makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, the shield sprouts roots and leaves and gains the resiliency of a willow tree, adding +2 to its Physical and Mystic Defense for the spell's duration.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Level: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+1 bonus), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+2 to its Physical and Mystic Defense</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Shield Willow</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">11</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">6</weaving>
				</id-00016>
				<id-00017>
					<casting type="string">Target's Mystic Defense</casting>
					<circle type="number">2</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell slows a weapon, reducing its ability to inflict damage. The magician mimes a slow-moving attack and then makes a Spellcasting test against the wielder's Mystic Defense. If successful, the air thickens around the target weapon and it slows each time it hits an opponent, causing the wielder to suffer a -4 penalty to his Damage tests. Nothing prevents the wielder from dropping the slowed weapon and swapping to another if he desires. Anyone picking up and using the weapon suffers the Damage test penalty until the spell ends.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Level: </b>Increase Duration (+2 Rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (-2 Damage penalty), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">-4 Damage test penalty</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Slow Weapon</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">10 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">11</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">6</weaving>
				</id-00017>
				<id-00018>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">3</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Water-Cold. </i>This spell creates an icy weapon that is thrown at an opponent. The magician hurls two pebbles, coins, or other objects at the target, then makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the objects transform into frozen spiked mace-heads joined by an icy chain, which wrap around the target. The magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted. If he rolls any Bonus Dice on the Damage test, the mace and chain shatter. If the mace and chain survive the blow, the target is Harried until he frees himself at the end of the following round.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">2 Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 2/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Ice Mace and Chain</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">12</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">7</weaving>
				</id-00018>
				<id-00019>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">3</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air-Electric. </i>This spell strikes the target with bolts of electricity. The magician raises his hands toward the sky, then points at the target and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, crackling bolts of electricity fly from the magician's fingers, striking the target. The magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted.</p>
						<p>The initial Spellcasting test is used against any additional targets that may result. Additional success levels on secondary targets will not cause additional bolts.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Additional Target (+1)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 Round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 6/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Lightning Bolt</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">12</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">7</weaving>
				</id-00019>
				<id-00020>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">3</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Water. Binding. </i>This spell summons a water elemental and temporarily binds it to a willing target. The magician looks into the target's eyes (or a mirror), touches them comfortingly, and makes a Spellcasting against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the target's eyes become placid and enticing as strong emotions leave them temporarily.</p>
						<p>The bound character may engage others in conversation and adopt their attitude and mannerisms in a flattering way, giving him a +4 bonus to Conversation tests. For every success, they may ask a general question regarding the target's attitude and feelings. The character may make multiple Conversation tests in this way, but for each subsequent test the Difficulty increases by +5. Subsequent tests may gather more specific information, though it must be directly relevant to the conversation (GM's discretion) and if the character fails a Conversation test, the spell ends immediately.</p>
						<p>If the bound character expresses any strong opinions or emotions not expressed by the target first, forcefully manipulates the interaction, or pressures the target, the spell immediately ends. If the spell ends prematurely for any reason, the bound character receives a -5 penalty to all Charisma-based tests until he receives a full night's rest, and this spell may not be cast again for a full day. This spell may only have one active casting at a time.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 to Conversation tests)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 10 minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Grant insight into a target through empathy</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Mantle of the Reflecting Pool</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">12</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">7</weaving>
				</id-00020>
				<id-00021>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">3</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Wood. </i>This spell converts any kind of plant material into a tasty feast. The spell requires three intact plants, no matter how scrawny.</p>
						<p>The magician cuts or tears the plants into small pieces, then makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, his Effect test determines the number of meals produced. Each meal has the following parts: appetizer, soup, salad, bread, entree, vegetable, and dessert. All of the meals are identical. Although they can appear to contain meat, none actually do. The meals are as nutritious and tasty as their real counterparts.</p>
						<p>The spell only creates types of food that the magician has tasted within the last year and a day - a good reason for him to occasionally eat fine food to excess. Uneaten meals vanish when the spell ends.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 hours), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step),</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank hours</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower +2</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Plant Feast</name>
					<threads type="number">3</threads>
					<range type="string">10 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">12</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">7</weaving>
				</id-00021>
				<id-00022>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">2-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">8</casting>
					<circle type="number">3</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>Wood. </b>This spell accelerates plant growth. The magician sprinkles water on the ground and makes a Spellcasting (8) test. If successful, plants in the area of effect experience the equivalent of one week's growth over the remainder of the round. After the spell ends, their growth rate returns to normal, but the plants do not revert to their normal size - the effect is permanent. This spell may only be cast a number of times equal to Spellcasting Rank per day and only once per affected area per week.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+1 day of growth), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 Round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Accelerates plant growth</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Thrive</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">12</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">7</weaving>
				</id-00022>
				<id-00023>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">3</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell creates a wall of swirling wind strong enough to deflect physical attacks. The magician makes whooshing noises and makes a Spellcasting test against his Mystic Defense. If successful, a wave of roiling and surging air surrounds him. The adept gains a +3 bonus to any Avoid Blow test. This spells allows Avoid Blow to be used against Blindside and Surprise attacks.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 bonus), Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Improves Avoid Blow tests</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Winds of Deflection</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Self</range>
					<reattune type="number">12</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">7</weaving>
				</id-00023>
				<id-00024>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">6 yards wide</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">4</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>Air. </b>This spell creates a howling blast of wind. The magician places both hands to his lips and blows hard, then flings his arms wide and makes a Spellcasting test against the highest Mystic Defense among anyone within range. If successful, a powerful blast of air surges away from the magician in a 6-yard wide line in the direction he is facing. Those caught in the wind's path must make a successful Knockdown test against the magician's Effect test to avoid being Knocked Down.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 Round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 5</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Air Blast</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">13</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">8</weaving>
				</id-00024>
				<id-00025>
					<circle type="number">4</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Water-Cold. </i>This spell conjures a small blizzard against foes. The magician shivers and rubs his shoulders, then cups his hands together as if holding a snowball and makes a Spellcasting test against the highest Mystic Defense among all targets in the area of effect. If successful, freezing ice, sleet, and snow fills the sphere, which remains stationary for the spell's duration.</p>
						<p>Movement is halved through the area of effect due to the conditions. Each round, the magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted on any targets within the area of effect.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 2/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Blizzard Sphere</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">30 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">13</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">8</weaving>
				</id-00025>
				<id-00026>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">Varies (see text)</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">4</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>Element [Air, Earth, Fire, Water, or Wood]. </b>This spell forms a spear from one of the elements. There is an Elemental Spear for each element: air, earth, fire, water, and wood. Each version of the Elemental Spear spell is learned separately, but can be held in the same spell matrix.</p>
						<p>The magician touches some of the desired element and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, a spear is formed from the element, which hurtles toward the target, striking him. The magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted. Regardless of the result, the spear dissipates after the attack.</p>
						<p>Each spear provides a different secondary effect.</p>
						<p> Air spears cause a clap of thunder when they impact the target. The Effect test is compared to the Mystic Defense of each character within 2 yards of the target. If successful, all affected characters suffer a -2 penalty to Action tests until the end of the next round.</p>
						<p> Earth spears force the target to resist Knockdown against a Difficulty Number equal to the total damage received after armor.</p>
						<p> Fire spears deal an additional Step 4/D6 damage die.</p>
						<p> Water spears heal instead of harm; the target may immediately spend a Recovery test with a +2 bonus (this may not be affected by other healing aids).</p>
						<p> Wood spears sprout entangling vines which cause the target to be Harried until the end of the next round.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Duration (+2 rounds, if applicable), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Varies (see text)</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 4/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Elemental Spear</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">13</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">8</weaving>
				</id-00026>
				<id-00027>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">4</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air-Electric. </i>This spell electrically charges the target, enhancing his movement. The magician must be standing under the open sky with wet feet. He rubs his feet back and forth on the ground, and then makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, coruscating green lightning surrounds the magician's feet. The target moves around on a sizzling, one-foot-wide lightning bolt that pops with every step, jumping him around from place to place, and adds +2 to his Initiative, Movement Rate and Physical Defense for the spell's duration.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+1 to all effects)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+2 to Initiative, Movement Rate and Physical Defense</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Lightning Step</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">13</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">8</weaving>
				</id-00027>
				<id-00028>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">4</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Wood. </i>This spell heals the target a small amount each round it is in effect. The magician holds some dried plant matter in his fingers, blows it away, and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the plant matter is returned to vibrancy and floats around the target briefly, surrounding them with a momentary green glow. Either the target or the magician must spend a Recovery test and the target heals 4 damage each round on their Initiative.</p>
						<p>Outside of combat, healing is reduced to 1 damage per round and is not affected by additional threads.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (+2 damage healed), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Grants the target continual healing</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Grove Renewal</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">10 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">13</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">8</weaving>
				</id-00028>
				<id-00029>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">10-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">4</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>Earth. </b>This spell makes the ground around the magician shake and move violently. The magician places his hands on the ground and makes a Spellcasting test that is compared against each Mystic Defense among any characters in the area of effect.</p>
						<p>If successful, the ground lurches suddenly and violently, causing affected targets to become Harried and their Movement Rate is halved (round down) until they move out of the area of effect or the spell ends. The magician is not affected by the shaking.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Area (+2 yards), Remove Targets (-Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Penalties to character actions</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Uneven Ground</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">Self</range>
					<reattune type="number">13</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">8</weaving>
				</id-00029>
				<id-00030>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">5</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell creates a quarterstaff from a handful of earth or a piece of stone, or emerging directly from the earth. The magician touches the material and then makes a Spellcasting test. If successful, a five-foot-long quarterstaff (with all equivalent attributes) is formed that can be used as a melee weapon in combat. The appearance of each earth staff is unique to the Elementalist and will change as he increases in Circle (generally becoming more distinctive and ornate). While the Earth Staff is in hand, all successfully cast Elementalism spells are treated as though they have an additional success. Only those with knowledge of Elementalism may wield the earth staff. If a character without Elementalism wields an earth staff in combat, the spell ends as soon as the staff is used, causing no effects, and reverting back to its original components.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Weapon Damage (+2 Steps)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 10 minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Increase successes on Elementalism spells</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Earth Staff</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">14</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">9</weaving>
				</id-00030>
				<id-00031>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">4-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">5</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Fire. </i>This spell creates an explosive ball of flame.</p>
						<p>The magician conjures a small flame and places one of his hands to the side of the fire, waving it in a circular motion over the top of the flame, then makes a Spellcasting test against the highest Mystic Defense among all targets within a 4-yard radius of the point of impact. If successful, a small globe of fire erupts from his hand, which quickly expands to the size of a beach ball, before exploding in an intense gout of flame at the point of impact. The magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted on those affected. Those affected are also Partially Blind (-2 penalty to Actions) until the end of the next round.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards), Remove Targets (-Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">2 Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Wilpower + 4/Physical and Partial Blindness</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Fireball</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">30 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">14</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">9</weaving>
				</id-00031>
				<id-00032>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">5</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Fire. </i>This spell rapidly heats up armor or shields. The magician rubs his hands together and makes a Spellcasting test against the wearer's Mystic Defense. If successful, the armor quickly heats to an extreme temperature. Each round, the magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted on those wearing or touching the armor (the wearer receives no protection from the armor affected by this spell).</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Heat Armor</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">14</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">9</weaving>
				</id-00032>
				<id-00033>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">100-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">5</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell uses Blood Magic to enhance the rate at which land grows food. The magician pricks his hand with a sharp object and lets a drop of blood fall on the earth, taking 1 Blood Magic Damage (this damage can be healed after the spell ends), then makes a Spellcasting test against the ground's Mystic Defense (usually 6). If successful, an area of soil up to 100 yards in radius is enriched by magic, making the land especially fertile for a year and a day. Plants grow in this soil at roughly double their normal rate - the gamemaster determines the exact effects of this growth.</p>
						<p>Many kaers survived the Scourge by using this spell and it enabled many towns rebuilt in areas prone to bad weather to thrive on the surface. Rumor has it that questors of Jaspree from the town of Trosk are attempting to heal the Badlands through liberal use of the Nutritious Earth spell.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Area (+10 yards)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Area (+10 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">A year and a day</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Makes land fertile</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Nutritious Earth</name>
					<threads type="number">4</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">14</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">9</weaving>
				</id-00033>
				<id-00034>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">5</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air - Electric </i>. This spell transports the magician to any location he can see within range. The magician's current location and destination both must be open to the sky.</p>
						<p>The magician points to his destination with one hand, then points to the sky with his other and makes a Spellcasting test against his Mystic Defense. If successful, lighting strikes him and the destination simultaneously, leaving a mark on the ground unique to the magician in each location. The magician is immediately transported to the destination. If the magician gets one success, he is disoriented and cannot act during the next round. On two successes, he may act normally on the following round. With three successes, he may immediately act as though he has not taken any actions yet this round. If the Spellcasting test fails, the magician is struck by lightning for WIL+6/Physical damage. Each additional use of this spell on the same day has a cumulative +5 modifier to the Casting Difficulty.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>See text.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Range (+2 miles)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Travel by lightning</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Ride the Lightning</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">Self: 4 miles</range>
					<reattune type="number">14</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">9</weaving>
				</id-00034>
				<id-00035>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">4-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">5</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell turns an ordinary stone into an explosive missile. The magician picks up a fist-sized stone, then throws it at the target and makes a Spellcasting test against the highest Mystic Defense of any character within the area of effect. If successful, the stone explodes into sharp fragments that scatter in all directions. The magician compares his Spellcasting test against the Mystic Defense of all characters within the area of effect. The Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted on each target, and all targets must make a Knockdown test against the damage taken.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 Round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 5/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Shattering Stone</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">14</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">9</weaving>
				</id-00035>
				<id-00036>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">2 yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">6</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Fire or Water-Cold. </i>This spell causes a radical change in ambient temperature. The magician wraps his arms about himself and shivers as if cold, then points toward the spot where the effect will be centered and makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, the temperature inside the area of effect rises to extreme hot or cold, causing water to either boil or freeze (as appropriate), at the magician's discretion. The temperature change takes thirty seconds to reach the final temperature, after which each round that a character is caught in or passes through the sphere of effect, the magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted. Once the spell has been cast, the sphere of effect cannot be moved. This spell is commonly used to create a barrier to discourage others from passing a given point.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 2/NA</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Drastic Temperature</name>
					<threads type="number">3</threads>
					<range type="string">40 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">15</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">10</weaving>
				</id-00036>
				<id-00037>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">6</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Fire. </i>This spell creates a protective cloak of flames. The magician makes stitching motions, then touches the target and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, a cloak of fire wraps around the target. Anyone attacking the wearer in close combat suffers damage each round from the intense heat thrown off by the cloak. The wearer makes an Effect test to determine how much damage is inflicted. The cloak's heat does not affect the wearer.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 2/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Fireweave</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">15</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">10</weaving>
				</id-00037>
				<id-00038>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">6</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Fire. Binding. </i>This spell summons a fire elemental and temporarily binds it to a willing target. The magician showers the target in sparks, then touches the target and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the target will bellow in rage and be engulfed in flame. Anyone engaging the target in close combat automatically takes Effect test damage (Physical Armor protects).</p>
						<p>The target's Damage tests add a bonus dice of fire damage equal to the Effect Step.</p>
						<p>Each round, the target must use the Aggressive Attack option (even if not normally allowed, such as when using ranged weapons), though this does not cost Strain. The target must either attack, or move their full movement toward their next opponent with every intention of attacking that opponent. Failure to do either of these causes the fire elemental to forcefully leave the target, dealing Effect Step +2 damage to the target (no armor protects).</p>
						<p>Any attempt to fool the elemental by not engaging an opponent in combat will cause the spell to immediately end as previously described. This spell may only have one active casting at a time and is incompatible with the Flameweapon and Fireweave spells. The magician may choose to reduce the Effect Step of the spell at the time of casting.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Elementalist + 2</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Mantle of the Fire Marauder</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">15</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">10</weaving>
				</id-00038>
				<id-00039>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">6</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth - Metal. </i>This spell creates shiny metal wings, which sprout forth from a character's shoulders, allowing him to fly. The magician touches the shoulder of the target, then spreads his arms wide and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, gleaming silver metal wings appear on the target's back. The wings allow him to fly at a Movement Rate of 12. Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 minutes) Earth - Metal. This spell creates shiny metal wings, which sprout forth from a character's shoulders, allowing him to fly. The magician touches the shoulder of the target, then spreads his arms wide and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, gleaming silver metal wings appear on the target's back.</p>
						<p>The wings allow him to fly at a Movement Rate of 12.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 Strength bonus), Increase Effect (+2 Movement Rate), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 10 Minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Flight; +6 bonus to Strength for lifting</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Metal Wings</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">15</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">10</weaving>
				</id-00039>
				<id-00040>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">2-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">6</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell showers fist-sized stones from the sky. The magician points at where the stones will fall and makes a Spellcasting test against the highest Mystic Defense among any characters within the area of effect. If successful, affected targets are struck by falling stones. The magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted. Each round, more stones rain down on the targets, who continue to take damage as long as they remain within the area of effect. Anyone that takes damage from this spell must make a Knockdown test against the damage taken. Movement Rates in the area of effect are halved.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 5/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Stone Rain</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">20 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">15</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">10</weaving>
				</id-00040>
				<id-00041>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">10-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">6</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell tosses those standing on an area of earth or stone wildly into the air. The magician makes loud noises as he hurls pebbles, dirt, or small stones on the ground, then makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, the area of effect becomes explosive when touched. The magician makes an Effect test. Each round, anyone moving through the area of effect makes a Willpower test against the test result. If successful, the character can move and act normally. If failed, the earth or stone beneath the character explodes, throwing him Step 5/D8 yards into the air, inflicting falling damage based on the height fallen (see the Gamemaster's Guide). The area remains volatile until the spell ends.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 hours)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Duration (+2 hours), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Effect (+2 Step distance), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards),</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank Hours</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Tossing Earth</name>
					<threads type="number">3</threads>
					<range type="string">40 Yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">15</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">10</weaving>
				</id-00041>
				<id-00042>
					<casting type="string">8+ (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">7</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell summons cloud cover as a precursor to casting another spell, such as Death Rain (p. 289), or simply to achieve impressive weather effects. The magician makes gestures mimicking the swirling pattern of rapidly-moving clouds, then tosses some water into the air and makes a Spellcasting test against a Difficulty Number determined by the cloud type. Summoning normal clouds carries a Casting Difficulty of 8; stormy weather carries a Casting Difficulty of 13; gale-force storms carry a Casting Difficulty of 20 (or more, at the gamemaster's discretion). If successful, the water billows into a wispy fragment of cloud, rising rapidly into the sky where it acts as a beacon drawing other clouds to it.</p>
						<p>Under normal circumstances, the clouds summoned take one hour to arrive -  storm clouds may take longer to gather. The magician makes an Effect test, subtracting the test Result in minutes from the clouds' arrival time. The spell may be cast multiple times to hasten the clouds' arrival. The effect centers on the magician's position at the time of his first casting - it does not move with the magician. The range also determines the radius of ground area covered by the clouds. The magician can summon any type of natural cloud formations he has witnessed or experienced. If he has not been outside during a storm, he cannot summon that type of weather.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 hours), Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank hours</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 6</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Cloud Summon</name>
					<threads type="number">3</threads>
					<range type="string">1 maile (see text)</range>
					<reattune type="number">16</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">11</weaving>
				</id-00042>
				<id-00043>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">20 yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">7</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Water-Acid. </i>This spell causes acid rain to fall from the sky. It requires cloud cover, either natural or produced by magic, such as the Cloud Summon spell, p.288. The magician calls out the Names of those friendly to him, then compares his Spellcasting test against the Mystic Defense of each un-Named target within the area of effect. If successful, corrosive rain falls from the clouds onto the target.</p>
						<p>Each round of exposure to the acid causes Step 8/2D6 damage to the target. The magician is unaffected, as are those whose Names were shouted when the spell was cast. If the magician chooses to concentrate, the acid's intensity increases and he adds his Willpower Step to the rain's Damage test that round. Once he breaks concentration, he cannot regain it again without recasting the spell. Even if the magician loses concentration, the spell continues until it ends. Should the magician move, the area of effect remains stationary.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Level: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Area (+2-yard radius)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Step 8 (Willpwer + 8; See text)/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Death Rain</name>
					<threads type="number">3</threads>
					<range type="string">Self</range>
					<reattune type="number">16</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">11</weaving>
				</id-00043>
				<id-00044>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">4-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">6</casting>
					<circle type="number">7</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell creates a wave of earth that hastens travel. The magician must be standing on earth or rock, then kneels down and moves his hands over the ground and makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, the area of ground on which he is standing becomes a wave of soil he can ride with a Movement Rate of 16 through areas without significant obstacles (boulders, trees, houses, etc). Encountering an obstacle will immediately end the spell (GM's discretion).</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+1 hour)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+1 hour), Increase Effect (+2 Movement Rate), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">2 hours</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Creates earth wave</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Earth Surfing</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">Self</range>
					<reattune type="number">16</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">11</weaving>
				</id-00044>
				<id-00045>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">7</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Wood. Binding. </i>This spell summons a wood elemental and temporarily binds it to a willing target. The magician stabs the target with a thorn and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, thorns erupt from the target's flesh and they immediately suffer a wound. However, the target is immune to Wound penalties for the duration of the spell. Consequently, many Horrors will ignore them for this time.</p>
						<p>The target may spend up to their Willpower Step in Strain to grow a number of 2 yard by 2 yard sections of brambles within 10 yards equal to amount of Strain spent. The brambles are fed on the target's blood and quickly grow from the ground, hungry for more blood. Any character, except for the bound character, who comes in contact with the brambles takes Step 4 damage; no armor protects against this damage.</p>
						<p>Success Levels: Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>Extra Threads: Increase Effect (+2 Damage Steps), Increase Range (from touch to 10 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Ignore Wound penalties and create temporary obstructions for a price paid in blood</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Mantle of the Blood Elf</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">16</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">11</weaving>
				</id-00045>
				<id-00046>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">6-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">7</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell creates a loud clap of thunder that stuns and deafens those hearing it. The magician claps his hands and compares his Spellcasting test against the Mystic Defense of each character, friend or foe, within the area of effect.</p>
						<p>If successful, the target suffers a -6 penalty to his Action tests until the end of the following round and is deafened for a further Step 6 rounds, during which he suffers a -6 penalty to his hearing-based Perception tests. Most unintelligent creatures flee in fear of the sound.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (-2 penalty), Increase Range (+2 yards), Remove Targets (-Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">2 rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">-6 penalty to Action tests; causes deafness</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Thunderclap</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">Self</range>
					<reattune type="number">16</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">11</weaving>
				</id-00046>
				<id-00047>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">4-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">6: TMD (see text)</casting>
					<circle type="number">7</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air. </i>This spell creates a spinning turbulent column of air. The magician makes whirling motions with his fingers and then makes a Spellcasting (6) test. If successful, he forms a swirling pillar of wind, 4 yards high, which spins wildly around him. Each round, the magician may concentrate to direct the whirlwind against one character in range. The magician makes a Spellcasting test against the highest Mystic Defense among all characters in the area of effect. If successful, his Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted. All targets in the area of effect are Harried. If the magician ceases to concentrate, the wind dissipates and the spell ends.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Range (+10 yards), Increase Area (+2 yards), Remove Targets (-Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 2/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Whirlwind</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">20 yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">16</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">11</weaving>
				</id-00047>
				<id-00048>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">8</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell causes a massive hand to rise out of the ground and seize a character standing on earth or stone, exerting injurious crushing force on him. The magician shakes a fist at the target and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the magician's Effect test determines how much damage is inflicted each round - this requires his concentration or the spell ends. Each round, the target may make a Strength test against the Effect Step to break free, otherwise, he may perform no other actions while held in the spell's grip.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Effect Step), Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Range (+10 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank rounds</duration>
					<effectStep type="string">Willpower + 2/Physical</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Crushing Hand of Earth</name>
					<threads type="number">2</threads>
					<range type="string">20 yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">17</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">12</weaving>
				</id-00048>
				<id-00049>
					<casting type="string">10</casting>
					<circle type="number">8</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth. </i>This spell summons an earthen wall. The magician must be standing on earth or stone making shoveling actions, as if digging a dirt palisade, and then makes a Spellcasting (10) test. If successful, he summons up to Spellcasting Rank contiguous wall sections, each 4 yards high, 2 yards wide, and 2 yards thick. Summoning and positioning a section takes the magician one round and requires his concentration. The wall may not be placed on a living being - doing so immediately destroys that section, which still counts toward the maximum number of wall sections summoned. The wall can be physically or magically attacked. Treat each section of wall as a barrier with Physical and Mystic Armor of 12 and a Death Rating 40.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 hours)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 hours), Additional Sections (+2), Increase Range (+10 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank hours</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Create a contiguous wall of earth</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Earth Wall</name>
					<threads type="number">3</threads>
					<range type="string">20 yards</range>
					<reattune type="number">17</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">12</weaving>
				</id-00049>
				<id-00050>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">8</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Earth - Metal. </i>This spell melds the target's body with a form of elemental metal, strengthening it. The magician grasps a piece of metal, crosses both fists and punches the target, then makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If the test succeeds, the target gains +3 to Physical Armor, Wound Threshold and Knockdown tests. The effects of this spell are reflected in the target's appearance, which takes on a dark, metallic look. Also, the target's weight effectively doubles and he loses all buoyancy, including the ability to swim (the spell in no way bolster's the target's respiratory processes, so casting on an ally while afloat would be a remarkably bad idea).</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (minutes), Increase Effect (+1 to all bonuses), Additional Targets (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+3 to Physical Armor, Wound Threshold and Knockdown test</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Ironskin</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">17</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">12</weaving>
				</id-00050>
				<id-00051>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">8</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Air - Electric. </i>Binding. This spell summons an air elemental and temporarily binds it to a willing target and requires cloud cover. The magician reaches to the sky with one hand and touches the target with his other hand, then makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, lightning will strike his upraised hand and travel to the target, lifting him from the ground as electricity courses through his body.The target gains a flying Movement Rate of 16 and can concentrate to surround himself with a 2-yard radius field of electricity which will levitate any willing targets in the area, allowing them to travel with him.</p>
						<p>When doing this, the bound target may only move and perform Free Actions.</p>
						<p>The bound target gains +2 to Initiative tests. The target's presence is always heralded and may not perform Blindside or Surprise attacks.</p>
						<p>If the target touches the ground for any reason, the spell immediately ends.</p>
						<p>If the spell ends prematurely for any reason, the target takes one Wound and this spell may not be cast again for a full day. This spell may only have one active casting at a time.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+10 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+10 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 Movement Rate), Increase Effect (+2 Initiative)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank x10 minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Target gains flight and increased speed</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Mantle of the Lightning Vanguard</name>
					<threads type="number">3</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">17</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">12</weaving>
				</id-00051>
				<id-00052>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">8</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Wood. </i>This spell enhances a melee weapon with elemental power. The magician shouts out a battle cry, then touches the melee weapon held by the target and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the melee weapon gleams bright green and appears oily and slick, adding +3 to Damage tests and poisoning the opponent if at least one point of damage is inflicted. The poison inflicts paralysis with an instant onset time, and a Mystic Defense and Step equal to the magician's Elementalist Circle+3. Effects of the poison wear off when the spell ends.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds), Increase Effect (+1 Damage bonus), Increase Range (+10 yards), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+3 to close combat Damage tests and poison</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Venomous Fury</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">17</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">12</weaving>
				</id-00052>
				<id-00053>
					<areaeffecttext type="string">10-yard radius</areaeffecttext>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">8</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<i>Water. </i>This spell heals all of the magician's allies within the area of effect. The magician kneels and places his palm on the ground, closes his eyes, sheds a tear and makes a Spellcasting test against the highest Mystic Defense in the area of effect. If successful, bright, sparkling effervescent water bubbles up from the ground in the area, disappearing into the sky as it refreshes everyone affected. All targets within the area may make a Recovery test. The magician may give his own Recovery tests to any targets (one per target) for use with this spell. Targets that do not have a Recovery Test available are unaffected.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Recovery test bonus)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Effect (+2 Recovery test bonus), Increase Area (+2 yards)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Elementalist</source>
					<duration type="string">1 round</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">Heals all allies within the area of effect</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Vital Springs</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">17</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">12</weaving>
				</id-00053>
				<id-00054>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>This spell increases resistance to fear. The magician thinks positive thoughts, then gently touches the target while murmuring something reassuring like "everything's going to be okay" and makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the target adds +3 to his Mystic and Social Defense against fear-causing attacks and gains a +3 bonus to any Willpower tests he makes to resist the effects of fear or Intimidation (see the Gamemaster's Guide).</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 rounds)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (minutes), Increase Effect (+2 bonus), Additional Target (+Rank)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Illusionist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 rounds</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+3 to Mystic and Social Defense; +3 Willpower test bonus against fear</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Assuring Touch</name>
					<threads type="number">0</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00054>
				<id-00055>
					<casting type="string">TMD</casting>
					<circle type="number">1</circle>
					<text type="formattedtext">
						<p>
							<b>
								<i>Illusion. </i>
							</b>
							<i>This spell disguises one's identity. The magician splashes water or cologne on the target's face then makes a Spellcasting test against the target's Mystic Defense. If successful, the target's face changes to match a face envisaged by the magician -  if he is copying a specific face, he must have seen that individual within the last month.</i>
						</p>
						<p>The target gains a +3 bonus to Disguise Self (and may use Disguise Self as a default skill if they do not possess it) or Charisma-based tests when trying to convince others of his false identity and attempting to persuade them to act according to that misperception. Any Interaction tests made against the target are considered Sensing tests (see Illusions, p.266). The spell only affects the target's head and neck, including hair and ears. The maximum possible size difference between the target's face and that being mimicked is 100 percent in any dimension - the magician must find another way to disguise obvious differences. The target's voice is unchanged, so he must try to mimic the speech characteristics of the character whose face he has borrowed as best he can.</p>
						<p>
							<b>Success Levels: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes)</p>
						<p>
							<b>Extra Threads: </b>Increase Duration (+2 minutes), Increase Effect (+2 bonus), Additional Target (+1)</p>
					</text>
					<source type="string">Illusionist</source>
					<duration type="string">Rank + 5 minutes</duration>
					
					<effectStep type="string">+3 bonus to Charisma-based tests</effectStep>
					<name type="string">Best Face</name>
					<threads type="number">1</threads>
					<range type="string">Touch</range>
					<reattune type="number">10</reattune>
					<weaving type="number">5</weaving>
				</id-00055>
			</category>
		</spelldata>